To sink or swim 生き残るために
Dog eat dog world だと言い聞かせる
What went wrong?
Surviving with the fate, it’s 弱肉強食
Face a world that our wisdom only will tell me
What went wrong
I’ve paid my dues, I’ve sold my soul
So tell me what is left for me
When I’ve given up everything
ねえ　取り替えてたんだろう
どの景色を見ても　何も感じなかったよ
ねえ　考え直しても
あの景色を求めていた　僕は無感情だろう
ねえ　取り替えてたんだろう
どの景色を見ても　何も感じなかったよ
ねえ　考え直しても
あの景色を求めていた　僕は無感情だろう
NORTHERN ENGLAND EARLDOM OF NORTHUMBRIA
VIKINGS' BASE
その日は土曜日で
It was a Saturday.
ヴァイキングたちは土曜日に風呂に入る
Vikings bathe on Saturdays.
彼らのその習慣をイングランド人は知っていた
The English knew about this custom.
てっ…敵襲だァァァーッ!!
Enemy attack.
焼き尽くせ!!
Burn them all.
女子供とて容赦するな!!
Don't spare the women or children.
皆殺しが王の御命令だ！
Kill them all. Those are the king's orders.
SWORD
持ちこたえろ！ ここが勝負どころだ！
Hang in there. This is it.
っしゃー！
Yeah.
スノーレ殺ったぞーっ！
I killed Snorre.
くっそ～
Damn.
よーし！ 槍部隊 前へーーっ！
All right. Spear troops, advance.
トツゲキーー！
Charge.
あーあ  戦場があっち行っちゃった
The battlefield went that way.
もー  何でいつもすぐにやられちゃうんだろ
Why do I always get killed so fast?
死体はしゃべっちゃダメだ  トルフィン
Dead men aren't supposed to talk, Thorfinn.
おまえいっつも真っ先に死ぬよな ファクシ
You're always the first one to die, Faxi.
ん～～
Yeah.
天国にある“ヴァルハラ”では毎日お肉が食べられるからね
In Valhalla, in heaven,
you get to eat meat every day.
強い戦士じゃないと“ヴァルハラ”には入れないんだぞ
You can't enter Valhalla
unless you're a strong warrior.
ん～～ そっか…
I see.
母上や姉上は行けるのかな  ヴァルハラ…
I wonder if my mother and my sister
will get into Valhalla.
やられたか トルフィン
Did they kill you, Thorfinn?
雪の上で死ぬとカゼをひくぞ
If you die in the snow, you'll catch a cold.
明日出発ぅ？
You're leaving tomorrow?
いーなーいーなー！ 今度どこ行くの？
You're so lucky. Where are you going this time?
ノルウェーさ  遊びじゃないぞ
To Norway. I'm not going there for fun.
商売に行くんだ
I'm going to trade goods.
毛織物や毛皮を持ってって ワインなんかと交換するんだ
I take wool and fur, and trade it for wine.
じゃーボクも行く
Then I'm going too.
だめ  じゃあってなんだ サラッと言うな
No. What do you mean, "then"?
Don't say it so casually.
ちェッ  ケーチ
What? You're so stingy.
流水にぶつかっても知らないかんね！
I don't care if you end up hitting an ice floe.
年末までにワインが欲しいんだよ
I want to get some wine before the end of the year.
本国のみんなとイエス・キリストの
I'm going to celebrate the birth of Jesus Christ
誕生日をワインで祝うんだ
with the people of my home country
with some wine.
ボクの父上はミードが好きだよ
My father likes mead.
わけてもらえば？
Ask him for some.
ワインを飲むことに意味があるんだ
It has to be wine.
あるいはこの村にワインがあるかと思ったんだがな
I thought there'd be some wine in this village, though.
トルフィン
Thorfinn.
一走り お前の父上に伝言を頼む
Can you pass on a message to your father for me?
ん？
What?
軍船が来た
A warship has come.
こんなもんでどうかな？ 親方
How's this, master?
今度はふさがったろ
The leak's been fixed this time.
水 入れてみな
Try putting some water in it.
難しいもんだなァ
This is difficult.
力を入れすぎなんだよ トールズさん
You put too much strength into it, Thors.
ちちうえーー！
Father.
父上
ここだ トルフィン
I'm over here, Thorfinn.
ちちうえ！
Father.
また軍船が来たよ！ スゲーでっかいヤツ！
Another warship came. It's huge.
“戦鬼”のトールズを出せって言ったきり あのままだ…
They asked for Thors the Troll.
They've been waiting there ever since.
トールズって… トールズさんだよな？
Thors? Are they talking about Thors?
戦鬼？
Troll?
しかしありゃ半可な連中じゃねえな
They're no amateurs.
ハーフダンたちみてぇなゴロツキとは違うぜ
They're not like Halfdan's thugs.
あ！ トールズさん！
Oh, Thors.
奴らこの村を攻める気じゃ…
Are they planning to invade this village?
ヨームの戦士たちよ！
Jomsvikings.
私はここだ！
I'm right here.
トールズさんに礼を…
They're bowing to Thors.
まさかここまで探しに来るとはな…
I never imagined you'd come this far looking for me.
フローキ
Floki.
ノルウェー遠征以来になりますな トールズ殿
We haven't seen each other
since the Norway campaign, Thors.
よもやこのような最果ての地におかくれとは…
I never imagined you'd be hiding here,
at the end of the earth.
用件を言え フローキ
Tell me your business, Floki.
では まずは上陸の許可を
Well, then. First give us your permission to land.
何者なんだろうなァ  トールズさんって…
Who is Thors?
若い頃に戦働きをしてたとは聞いたけど…
I heard he used to work on the battlefield
when he was young.
声がデケーよ アーレ
They'll hear you, Ari.
あんまり自分のことを話さない人だからなぁ
He doesn't talk about himself much.
おーい！ オレにも見せろよ
Let me see.
“ヨームの戦士たち”って言ってたよな
He said "Jomsvikings," right?
お前知ってるか？
Know anything about them?
さぁー…
Not really...
なんか父上 怒ってる？
Father is angry.
入浴の最中を狙っての奇襲だったということです
They made a surprise attack while they were bathing.
デーンロー各地で多くのデンマーク人が イングランド軍に殺害されました
Many Danes were killed
by English troops in Danelaw.
そしてその中には
Gunhilde,
デンマーク国王スヴェンの妹君
the sister of Sweyn,
グンヒルド様もいたとのこと…
the King of Denmark, was one of the victims.
妹の仇討ち…
Revenge for his sister.
スヴェン王はよい口実を得ました
King Sweyn has a good excuse now.
大きな戦が始まります
A big war is about to begin.
我ら戦士の出番です
It's time for us warriors to shine.
いくさ！
-War?
-Quiet.
シッ！
ヨーム戦士団はデンマーク軍と連合します
The Jomsvikings will join the army of Denmark.
来る春にはイングランドへの進攻が始まりましょう
Our invasion of England will begin
this coming spring.
好きにするがいい
Do what you will.
ここは北の最果ての小村だ
This is a small village
at the northern edge of the world.
北海の向こうで大国同士が何をしようと 関わりはない
Whatever these big countries on the other side
of the North Sea decide, it's none of my business.
そうはまいりません
That will not do.
我が首領シグヴァルディの命令は“全艦隊ヨムスボルグに集結せよ”
Our leader Sigvaldi ordered me
to gather the entire fleet at Jomsborg.
例外はない
No exceptions.
おわかりかな？
Do you understand?
その者がたとえ脱走兵といえどもね
Even if that man deserted the army.
脱走…
Deserted?
ヨーム戦士団大隊長
Captain of the Jomsvikings.
戦鬼のトールズ
Thors the Troll.
この度の戦…
This is a war...
あなたも参戦するのです
in which you too will fight.
トールズ殿
Thors.
この度のことは我が首領の温情なのですよ
Our leader is doing this out of his own goodwill.
15年前行方不明になったあなたが
After going missing 15 years ago,
この度晴れて戦線に復帰する
you have a chance
to return to the battlefield with honor.
すべてを不問にしてそういうことにしてくださるというのです
Our leader is willing to overlook everything.
我が首領はそれほどに あなたの腕を惜しまれている
That's how much our leader wants you.
それを伝えるために 軍船で来ることはあるまい
You didn't have to come on a warship
just to tell me that.
村の者が動揺している
The villagers are afraid.
お変わりになられましたな あのトールズ殿が…
You've changed a lot, Thors.
あるいはこの村が変えたのか…
Or did this village change you?
逃げろ！
-Run away.
にげろーっ！
やべやべっ
He's scary.
よい村だ
This is a nice village.
子供の様子でわかる
I can tell from the children.
戦災とは 今日まで無縁だったのでしょうな
They've lived a life free from war, until today.
聞いたか？ 戦だぞ！
Hear that? There's going to be a war.
スッゲェ！
-Wow.
-This is my first war.
オレ初めてだよ！
わざわざ海越えてトールズさんを誘いにきたんだぜアイツら！
He came all the way across the ocean to invite Thors.
スゲーよお前の親父さんは！
Your father is amazing.
でもよぉ… オレら連れてってもらえるかなぁ？
But I wonder if he'd take us with him.
オメェは無理だな 弱えェもん
You have no chance. You're weak.
んだよそれー！
-What are you talking about?
-You're no good unless you're strong.
やっぱ強くねーとダメかぁ
まぁその点オレは大丈夫だな
Well, I got that covered.
お前ら人を斬ったことねーだろ
You've never killed anyone, right?
そーゆー経験があるかないかで…
It all depends on whether
you've had that experience or not.
あ！ワリ…
Sorry.
私もね
I'm not just...
子供の使いじゃないんですよ
a powerless messenger, you know.
あなたがこたびの戦に加わらぬとおっしゃるなら
If you're saying you're not going to fight in the war,
私は主命を果たせぬし 我が首領の面目も潰れる
I can't carry out my master's orders,
and our leader's reputation would be damaged.
そうなれば とても手ぶらでは帰れません
I can't go back empty-handed in a situation like that.
おわかりでしょう？
You understand, don't you?
ヨーム戦士団
The Jomsvikings.
ヴェンドランドの港町 ヨムスボルグに
They're an army with a base in Jomsborg,
基地を持つ軍団だ
a port town in Wendland.
トールズが昔
I never imagined
ヨームの戦士だったとはな
that Thors used to be a Jomsviking.
強いんすか？
Are they strong?
強い
They're strong.
あまりに強くて
They're so strong
ヴェンドランド王などは彼らから税金を取れないでいるほどさ
that the King of Wendland was unable
to collect taxes from them.
北海最強を自負する軍団だ
They take pride in being the strongest army
in the Northern Sea.
撤収！ 全隊船に戻れ！
Withdraw. All troops, return to the ship.
撤収ー！
Withdraw.
なに今の？ カンジ悪いな
What was that just now? That was weird.
助かったな アーレ
You've been saved, Ari.
聞かれよ村の衆！
Listen, villagers.
私はヨーム戦士団のフローキだ
I'm Floki of the Jomsvikings.
主命により勇者
At the orders of my master,
トールズ・スノーレソンに
I have come to this land
加勢を頼むためこの地へ参った
to ask the hero Thors Snorresson to join our forces.
勇者…
Hero?
トールズ殿は！
Our leader has requested
我が首領の求めに応じられ 軍船1隻の提供を約束なされた！
that Thors be provided with one warship.
我と思わん者は
If you have what it takes,
トールズ殿とともに ヨムスボルグへ参られよ！
join Thors and come with us to Jomsborg.
ではトールズ殿！
Farewell, Thors.
いずれ戦場で会いましょうぞ！
We shall meet on the battlefield.
戦だっっっ！
We're going to war.
いやいや何十年ぶりかのう  えっ！？
-How many decades has it been?
-What?
おっしゃあ殺ったるでー！
I'm going to kill them all.
戦場に果てるは男の本懐よ！
It'll be an honor to die on the battlefield.
そうと決まれば明日っから船の準備だ！
Let's get started right away.
Let's prepare the ships tomorrow.
断れなかったのかね？ トールズ
I guess you couldn't say no, Thors.
村を巻き込んでしまったな…
I dragged the village into this.
昔…
A long time ago,
人を殺すことで身を立てていた
I used to earn my living by killing people.
でもある日…
But one day...
ある日 急に嫌になったんだ
One day, I suddenly hated it all.
殺すのも
I didn't want to kill
殺されるのも…
or be killed.
だから逃げたんだ
That's why I ran away
戦場から…
from the battlefield.
死んだようにうまく見せかけたつもりだったんだがな
I thought I succeeded in making it look like I died.
だったらもう一度…
You could do that again.
逃げればこの村がオレの代わりに報復される
If I run away, this village will be punished in my place.
ヨームの掟は脱走者を許さない
The Jomsvikings never forgive deserters.
自分のしてきたことに
The time has come
けじめをつける時が来たんだ
for me to take responsibility
for what I've done.
おーし引くぞー！
All right. Ready?
せェェェのォ！
One, two...
よいしょーっ！
Heave, ho.
よい
おら引けーっ！
Pull.
よいしょおーっ！
Heave, ho.
あれ  レイフさん今日出港じゃなかったっけ？
What? I thought you were leaving today, Leif.
トールズに頼まれたんだ
Thors asked me.
その軍船と船団を組むことにしたよ
I decided to join the fleet with that warship.
そうかぁ
I see.
確かにその方が安全だ
That would be safer.
イザって時はオレらが守ってやるからよ
We'll protect you in a pinch.
よっと
Here we go.
そりゃ頼もしい
I'm counting on you.
引け引けーっ！
Pull. Pull.
よいしょおーっ！
Heave, ho.
しかしまぁ
Though,
どいつも戦好きなことよ
everyone really does love war.
痛いよぉー！
You're so mean.
くっそぉトルフィンのやつ！
Darn you, Thorfinn.
囲め囲め！
Surround him.
くぬヤロ！
Bastard.
やった！ やった！ トルフィン…
We did it. I killed Thorfinn.
いってぇぇーっ！
That hurt.
なんだよ死ねよ トルフィン！ 今やられただろー！
What's wrong with you? Die, Thorfinn.
You got killed just now.
ルール守れよな！
Follow the rules.
そうだそうだ！
That's right.
なんだこいつ！
What's wrong with you?
大丈夫か？
Are you okay?
待てよトルフィン！
Wait, Thorfinn.
よーし！ 上げるぞーっ！
All right. Lift.
いちにのっさんっ！
One, two, three.
ようし！ もう一度いくぞ！
All right. One more time.
トールズ！
Thors.
ちょっと診てやってくれないか
Can you take a look at this?
イダーーッ！
The pain.
折れてるな
It's broken.
子供の遊びにしちゃやりすぎだ
Someone hit too hard.
It's supposed to be a game.
ひと月の間 添え木をしておいてくれ
Keep the splint on for one month.
すまんなトールズ
Sorry, Thors.
トルフィンがやったんだよ！
Thorfinn did it.
あいつ最近ムカつくんだ！
He pisses me off.
手加減しねーし
He's too rough.
もー絶対仲間に入れてやんねー！
I'm never playing with him again.
本当か？ ウチの子が？
Is that true? My son did this?
うん…ウゥ…
Yes.
そ…それはすまなかった
I'm sorry.
よく言って聞かせる
I'll talk to him about this.
気にすんなョ
Don't take it so seriously.
子供同士のことだ
It's between the kids.
でもまだ6つだろ？
He's only 6, right?
4つ5つ上の子たちにケガさせるたぁ
If he can hurt kids
that are four or five years older than him,
たいしたもんだよ
he must be pretty strong.
いい戦士になるぜあの子は
He'll grow up to be a good fighter.
やっぱりあんたの血だよ トールズ
He takes after you, Thors.
これ一式くれんの？ オヤジ！
You're giving me all of this, Dad?
ははっ じいさまの代からの家宝の武具だ
They're family treasures from my grandfather.
存分に戦ってこい！
Fight with all your might.
アーレ
Ari.
かっけーぞ アーレ
You look good, Ari.
オレのも見てくれ
Look at mine.
馬の首を一撃で落としたっつー名品だぜ
It can cut off a horse's head in one stroke.
おー！ デケェな
Wow, it's huge.
エモノったら槍だよ
Spears are what's best for plundering.
おー？ なんなら勝負すっか？
Really? Want to have a match?
もーあんたって子はぁ！
What's wrong with you?
なんでもかんでも放りっぱなしにすんなよな！
Don't throw everything on the floor.
ってコラ聞いてんの？
Hey. Are you listening to me?
片づけないと捨てちゃうよ！ いいの？
I'm going to throw it away
if you don't pick it up. Got it?
いい  もういらない
Go ahead. I don't want it anymore.
なんなのよ物置ひっくり返して
What are you doing,
searching through the storage room?
ウチの武器はどこ？
Where are our weapons?
はぁ？ ブキ？
What? Weapons?
ボクには武器が必要なんだ
I need a weapon.
武器があれば…
If I had a weapon...
あんた さては
Are you thinking...
戦士になって父上の船に乗せてもらっちゃおーとか考えてる？
you're going to become a warrior
and sail on your father's ship?
ゆっとくけどねー ムダな努力よ
I'm telling you now,
don't waste your time trying.
あんたみたいなチビッ子が
A little kid like you can't do it.
トルフィン？
Thorfinn.
きれい…
It's beautiful.
なに？ どうしたのユルヴァ
What is it? What's wrong, Ylva?
剣が欲しいか トルフィン
Do you want a sword, Thorfinn?
剣は人を殺す道具だ
A sword is a tool for killing people.
お前はこれで  誰を殺すつもりなんだ？
Who were you planning to kill with this?
てっ… 敵
The... The enemy.
お前の敵は誰なんだ？
Who is your enemy?
ハ…
Like...
ハーフダンとか…
Halfdan.
よく聞け トルフィン
Listen closely, Thorfinn.
お前に敵などいない
You don't have any enemies.
誰にも敵などいないんだ
No one has any enemies.
傷つけてよい者など どこにもいない
There's no one who it's okay to hurt.
おっ… おかしいよそんなの
You're wrong.
だって父上は明日いくさに行くんでしょ！
Father, you're going off to war tomorrow.
敵を殺しに行くんでしょ？
You're going to kill the enemy, right?
こどもじゃない…！
I'm not a kid anymore.
父上はウソを言ってる…
You're lying, Father.
ボクにだってわかる！
I can tell.
トルフィン！
Thorfinn.
うわっ トルフィン？
スキあり！ あぶねーって
-You let your guard down.
-That was dangerous.
Hey.
You made me bleed.
ヘルガ…
Helga.
はい
Yes?
あの子を…頼む
Take care of him for me.
西北西から微風
The wind blows faintly from the west north-west.
波 穏やか
The waves are calm.
今朝はオーディン神の機嫌がいい
Odin is in good spirits this morning.
出港にはいい朝だな…
This is a good morning for your departure.
ああ…
Indeed.
FAROE ISLANDS
STREYMOY
よぉーし言ったな！
You said it.
左手で投げて命中ならその酒ダルはオレのもんだぞ
If I throw left-handed and hit it,
the barrel is mine.
-No way.
-You can talk after you hit it.
おお… 主よ
I beg you, God...
いくぞ～キリスト坊主
Here I go, Christian monk.
よけたら殺すぞ～
If you dodge, I'll kill you.
てんめ！ よけたろ？ 今よけたろ？ 殺す！ マジ殺す！
You bastard. You dodged.
You dodged just now. I'm going to kill you.
どけよ 次はオレだ
Move. It's my turn.
ああ… 神父さま…
Oh, no. The priest...
だからよけんじゃねっつの！
I told you not to dodge.
おめぇがヘタなんだろ！
You're just bad.
オォイ！ ヨームの兄さん方！
Hey, Jomsvikings.
あんたらも一杯やらねえか？
Want to have a drink?
お行儀がよくていらっしゃる
They have good manners.
ほっとけ
Leave them alone.
安酒はお口に合わねんだとよ
They said they don't like cheap alcohol.
おりゃ！
Hey.
How many points do I get for his leg?
相変わらず貴様の手下は品がないな  アシェラッド
Your men don't have any class, Askeladd.
キリスト教が好かねぇだけですよ フローキのだんな
We just hate Christians, Floki.
それより… さっさと仕事の話をしましょうや
Enough about that. Let's get down to business.
手下どももオレも こんな僻地で待たされて退屈してたんです
My men and I are bored of being kept here waiting
in the middle of nowhere.
大きな変更はない
There are no major changes.
報酬は金5ポンド
You will be compensated with five pounds of gold.
奴の死体と引き換えでなければ払わんぞ
I will only pay you in exchange for his dead body.
奴の船と積み荷はお前たちの好きにしていい
You can do whatever you want with their ship,
and their cargo.
トールズを殺せ
Kill Thors.
It’s just like a burning torch in the storm
Like a little flower blooming in the home
強く確かな意志を掲げ
ときに優しくあればいい
I’m missing you
滲む景色に膝を抱き
胸をはせる時
Listen to me, sail away again
未開の海に回路を照らす願い
繋いだ声は　答えのない世界へと
帆を揺らす You’re not alone
ただ荒波をゆけ
その闇に向け